<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog</title>
  
  <subtitle>A place to express my thoughts on various topics</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://www.vivek.nl/"/>
  <updated>2019-12-25T10:40:08.099Z</updated>
  <id>http://www.vivek.nl/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Vivek Yadav</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Stuck at the locality</title>
    <link href="http://www.vivek.nl/2016/01/13/Stuck-at-the-locality/"/>
    <id>http://www.vivek.nl/2016/01/13/Stuck-at-the-locality/</id>
    <published>2016-01-13T14:15:29.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-12-25T10:40:08.099Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://www.vivek.nl/2015/10/03/Genetic-Algorithms-Some-Experiments/">my previous post</a>, I mentioned about working on a new type of genetic algorithm.<br>I went ahead and completed the program and tested it against data sets taken from <a href="http://comopt.ifi.uni-heidelberg.de/software/TSPLIB95/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TSPLIB</a>.</p><p>At first the results were promising, especially on the ATT48 dataset, but on trying out other data sets, I realized my algorithm was getting stuck at local minima. I tried increasing the population size and various combination of parameters but it would still end up in a minimum.</p><p>I left it at that point for some time. Recently, I have started work on it again.<br>There is something known as Niching in Genetic Algorithms. I plan to use it in my algorithm and see if there is any improvement (I hope there is).</p><p>By the way, coming to the programming language for this, it’s all in C++; had to be, if it’s CPU intensive then there is only 1 language for me, C++. The standard library has been good enough for me, except for logging. For that purpose, I have used <a href="https://github.com/gabime/spdlog" target="_blank" rel="noopener">spdlog</a>.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vivek.nl/2015/10/03/Genetic-Algorithms-Some-Experiments/&quot;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned about working on a new
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Genetic Algorithms: Some Experiments</title>
    <link href="http://www.vivek.nl/2015/10/03/Genetic-Algorithms-Some-Experiments/"/>
    <id>http://www.vivek.nl/2015/10/03/Genetic-Algorithms-Some-Experiments/</id>
    <published>2015-10-03T14:15:29.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-12-25T10:40:08.099Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>These past few months I have been trying out <em>Genetic Algorithms</em>.<br>They are a very interesting, relatively simple but powerful set of algorithms which can be used to find approximate solutions to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NP-hardness" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NP-hard</a> problems.</p><p>Now, a genetic algoeithm can be broken down to these simple steps:</p><ol><li>Generate a sample population</li><li>Crossover</li><li>Mutate</li></ol><p>Recursively doing steps 2 &amp; 3 and selecting the healthier candidates at each step, till you don’t see improvements across multiple iterations.<br>The secret is that such algorithms explore a much larger space in a given time period, compared to a deterministic algorithm.<br>You can find more detailed explainations at other places on the internet so I won’t repeat it.<br>I’ll focus a specific aspect, the mutation step.</p><p>Just like the crossover part, there are multiple ways to do it. People are experimenting with new ideas.<br>I got one such idea from a friend of my girlfriend. He called it “Supervised Mutation”.<br>Usually the mutation step is randomized in some way, but he put in a deterministic algorithm. So it is basically combining the powers of randomized and deterministic algorithms.</p><p>For some reasons he couldn’t take his research to conclusion, but I got interested in it. Hence I have been working on it, along with my girlfriend, during the past few months, although irregularly.</p><p>I have the code ready and have been trying to solve some <em>Travelling Salesman Problem</em>s, but I need my results to be standardized and comparable to others.<br>Now how would I do that ? By solving the same problems that others have solved; that way we can compare how efficienct our new algorithm is.<br>Problem was there are thousands of TSP problems.<br>Thankfully, I came across something known as <a href="http://comopt.ifi.uni-heidelberg.de/software/TSPLIB95/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TSPLIB</a>. A library of problems including, Symmetric/Asymmetric traveling salesman problem, Hamiltonian cycle problem (HCP), Capacitated vehicle routing problem (CVRP) and some other related category of problems.<br>Just the thing I was looking for.</p><p>So it is still a work in progress and I’ll post my findings here, along with code details, later.<br>But it sure is a refreshing change from what I do at my job at Amazon.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;These past few months I have been trying out &lt;em&gt;Genetic Algorithms&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;They are a very interesting, relatively simple but powerful 
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>So it beings...</title>
    <link href="http://www.vivek.nl/2015/10/03/So-it-beings/"/>
    <id>http://www.vivek.nl/2015/10/03/So-it-beings/</id>
    <published>2015-10-03T04:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-12-25T10:40:08.099Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I plan to blog here regularly or at least that is what I have told myself.<br>This blog is setup using hexo, for html generation, and github pages, for hosting.<br>I went this way instead of wordpress so as to do justice to the hackers inside me.<br>I hope he will be satisfied.</p><p>My next blog post is going to be on my work with <em>Genetic Algorithms</em>. Stay tuned.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;I plan to blog here regularly or at least that is what I have told myself.&lt;br&gt;This blog is setup using hexo, for html generation, and git
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
